The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: So
today, we really kind of talk
more about the system, the
kind of third direct innovation
factor, and then about
these indirect factors that
are important and significant,
but not as powerful, I'd argue,
as the direct factors.
But first, let me just
recap last week just really
in a few seconds,
and then give us
a glimpse of what
we're getting into.
So last week, Robert Solow,
the great growth economist,
developed-- really
created growth economics--
developed the theory that
the dominant causative
factor in economic
growth was, quote,
technological and
related innovation,
a phrase that you'll
hear all the time here.
And then we followed up
that discussion with talk
about Paul Romer and his
work on human capital
engaged in research as a kind
of second key direct innovation
factor.
That's the talent base that has
to be behind the R&D system.
We read Dale Jorgenson who
told us that, yes, in fact,
this innovation based
economic growth model
is in fact correct.
That's what happened
in the IT wave
and he showed us, in
effect, how that occurred.
The model was you do an
invention or a core group
of inventions, they
begin to scale up,
applications pile on them,
they enter into the economy
and really begin to
scale up in the economy.
And eventually, over time,
become a true innovation wave.
And we'll talk more today, as
you know, about innovation wave
theory.
We also read a piece by
some Merrill Lynch analysts,
and the fundamental
point in that piece
was that industry is very
interested in innovation,
but they're only prepared to
fund the very short late stage
of it.
So somehow, even though
the evolution to innovation
is a very long-term process,
the financial sector
is only going to
dive in as close
as they can to certainty--
in other words,
at a very late stage.
So those were kind of
our four core readings.
And one other idea in
that Merrill Lynch piece
was this notion that
innovation needs
to move through a series of
stages to kind of get there.
There needs to be
an early vision--
kind of a visionary who will
set out what could happen.
And then enabling
technologies evolve
that become technical
enablers for the evolution
to an innovation wave.
And then there's going to be
substantial talent on task.
In other words, people have
got to be-- researchers
have got to be working on this
in significant depth in order
for this thing to evolve.
So it's going to take a
community scale kind of effort.
So the first class
left us with two
direct or explicit
innovation factors.
And we could in a--
oversimplify them and
put them in shorthand,
but we could say
you've got to do R&D
and you've got to have a talent
base staffing that R&D system.
And we worked on a definition
of innovation as a system
for introducing
technical advance,
and we talked briefly about
innovation waves, which
we'll spend more time on today.
So that's a quick recap
of last week's discussion.
And Chris, you and
I can follow up
so you catch up on some of
the issues that came up there.
And I've posted the slides
to the STELLAR site which
will help as well, but I'd be
happy to talk to you further
about it.
So let me just do
a quick snapshot
to open up today's discussion.
So that's Thomas Edison.
That's his idea factory
and that's the group
that does the light bulb.
It's the light bulb
and you can see
the idea factory-- this building
in that scheme at the top.
And then you can
see the farmhouse
back behind which
is where Edison
lived with his wife except that
he never spent any time there.
He was in the idea
factory pretty much 24/7.
I just want to give
you a feel for what
innovation is like when
it starts to take off.
And this is a good--
Edison is a classic example.
So he-- very limited education.
He was homeschooled
by his mother.
He's probably pretty dyslexic.
We don't quite know that,
but it's probably the case.
As a kid, he understands
the early evolution
of the telegraph and he develops
kind of a newspaper sales
scheme during the
Civil War where
he gets the newspapers
ahead of time in Cleveland,
gets them out to the trains
coming into Cleveland,
and then sells
them on the trains.
And he's kind of kept--
in other words, he kind
of beats the news cycle
and then unloads newspapers on
these early commuting efforts
as people are coming
into the city.
He gets his big
break by scooping up
the child of the
telegraph operator.
So trains had to operate
by telegraph systems--
they were a crucial technology
to enable trains to work.
And the telegraph operator for a
train system is very important,
but also obviously serves a
larger community communications
purpose.
So the kid of the
telegraph operator
is down on the tracks--
train is coming down the tracks.
Edison, as a boy,
sees what's happening,
rushes, scoops the child up,
barely escapes the train.
Needless to say, the
telegraph operator
is appreciative, so he
trains Edison in Morse code
and how telegraph
operations work.
So he becomes an expert on
telegraph, which is obviously
early electrical technology.
And he becomes a master
at it, and then he
becomes very interested
in technology itself.
So over time, he
goes to New York--
he develops what
becomes, in effect,
an early stock
ticker, which can--
what we would call multiplex.
In other words, you could
receive multiple telegraphing
signals and communications
over the same line, which
obviously was a key enabler
for keeping track of stocks.
So he becomes very close to
the scions of Wall Street,
including JP Morgan.
He gets to know them all
because he's like their enabler.
And then he sees this thing
in Ansonia Connecticut.
It's not-- it's a much
bigger version of this,
but there's this
kind of gimmick--
these nine foot tall
polls with a spark,
because they're
positive and negative
a spark travels across--
looks really cool.
People are wondering
around-- they
don't know what to do
with it, but they're
awestruck by this kind of
electric movement of lightning
going across the two poles.
Edison has the idea-- oh, light.
So he takes the-- he makes
his money on Wall Street,
he takes all his money out.
He goes off into a farm
in Menlo Park, New Jersey
out into this rural area.
He hires this team which
consists of an interesting mix
of artisans--
like, there's an incredibly
important glass blower here,
which heralds back to the
MIT glass lab which I always
buy stuff from.
And there's also
scientists and engineers
in here, but a lot
of people who just
know how to do things
who are very good at sort
of mechanical tinkering.
And it's an interesting
team, and he
has to take this idea
of this weird arc
that he saw-- these nine
foot tall couple of poles
that he saw in
Ansonia Connecticut
and turn it into a light bulb.
It's not an easy job
and it's very intense.
There's only a certain
amount of money--
the money is going to run out.
He's gotta get this thing done
before he runs out of cash.
And they work
literally all the time.
They're always on it but they're
having the time of their lives.
So there's a wood
stove in here over in--
I'm not sure-- maybe
it's in another corner.
But around midnight, they all
gather around the wood stove
and they're--
rap music has not
been invented yet,
so they do doggerel verses which
they throw at one another--
insulting and funny and
this incredible doggerel
verse back and forth going on.
And they all have big cherry
pies and apple pies at midnight
and gather around the stove.
It's a very intense effort.
And actually, Edison
is away for so long
from the farmhouse which is
further back on the property
that at one point, when he
comes in at like 2:00 o'clock
in the morning, his wife
pulls a revolver on him
thinking he's an
intruder because she's
seen him so rarely.
Fortunately, she doesn't shoot.
But there they are gathered
on the idea factory,
and eventually they come
up with the core concepts.
The vacuum tube
obviously is core here
and the right
filament is core here.
They come up with a working
model of the electric light.
There's only one problem--
there's no electrical system.
There's no nothing.
So they've got a
wonderful application
for a nonexistent system.